Grygum: Hello!
Thorin: I think Zoom changed some defaults, because when I joined, I… my camera didn't show, and my microphone was off, so…
Grygum: It's always doing something different for me.
Thorin: Yeah.
Thorin: How are you?
Grygum: Oh, I'm… I'm doing good. We, we finally have, like, some… some furniture here. We, we now have a, like, a rug and a dining room table, and…
Grygum: It's starting to look like a… like a house, and not like a… Great big empty place.
Thorin: Was this one of those where, like, your old furniture didn't fill the space, or it didn't work, or, like…
Grygum: Well, we went from a place that was 800 square feet to a place that's 5,000 square feet.
Thorin: Oh yeah, so you, like, can fill a corner of it.
Grygum: Yeah, yeah.
Thorin: It's interesting, for our new place, because we were going super high-end and fancy, like, we hired interior designers, because you're like, I don't, you know, I want to do the whole thing.
Thorin: And their default mode was like, of course you're buying new furniture for everything.
Thorin: And so, we got rid of a lot of our old furniture, you know, some of it we moved into an ADU that we have,
Thorin: Here, right? Because we're like, I don't want to spend, like, top dollar on new furniture for the EDU. But a lot of it, like, we're like, alright, we'll trust the people, but I feel bad because a lot of our old furniture, we got rid of stuff that we've had for a long time, and, you know, you don't get any money for old furniture, so… but…
Thorin: I do love the results, so…
Grygum: Yeah, well, we're…
Grygum: I guess we're… I feel like we're kind of quirky, whimsical people, and I'm not sure how I'd quite communicate it to an interior designer, so…
Thorin: Well, so Rachel wanted… so our… our new house is kind of modern-like, but we wanted to have a Northwest vibe, so there's a lot of, like, woods and stuff like that in there, and, like, the designer's default was gonna be, like, I don't know, like.
Thorin: beige and white or something like that, right? And we're like, no, we want more color, we want more color, we want more color, and the architect
Thorin: wants these, like, clean lines and shadows and shit. I'm like, okay, you can live in the house then, like, you know
Thorin: And but the one thing was Rachel's office. She's like, I want it to be wild. I want it to feel like…
Thorin: like, an old sort of Victorian study with, like, lots of stuff, and so we were traveling in France.
Thorin: And she found this… we were in this bar, and they had this lamp, was this, like, gold monkey.
Thorin: like, with a…
Grygum: Lightbulb.
Thorin: smoke coming out of his head, like, holding a lampshade, right? The thing's fucking awesome.
Thorin: And we're, like, in this bar, and we're like, oh man, that lamp is so awesome. And we were there with friends, and the friends went to this store, and they were selling the damn lamp. And so we bought the monkey lamp.
Thorin: And we shipped it back to the U.S, and it had a European plug on it, and so I had to rewire it, and did you know that the European light bulb fittings are slightly different from U.S, but close enough that you can actually sort of, like, YOLO it, and the bulbs are interchangeable?
Grygum: -Oh, is that right?
Thorin: Yeah, it's like a 55 versus 56 on the bulb standard, or whatever, right? And I'm just like, you look at these lamps, and you're like, it's nothing but, like, you plug it into the wall, and it delivers it to the light bulb, so, like, 110, 220, who gives a shit, right?
Thorin: And so…
Thorin: So we told the designers, we're like, design the room around this lamp, and so the whole thing is really cool.
Thorin: And… and then we were showing it to the original architect, and he's like, well, this isn't gonna fit with the right of… with the rest of the house. And Rachel's like, fuck you, Lane, it's my office, this is what I want.
Thorin: I don't think she said fuck you, but definitely it came across.
Grygum: Did, did I, did I show you the, the lip?
Grygum: Architecture.
GM: Did the architect object to your choices?
Thorin: Yes, because we were ruining the aesthetic of his house, and I'm like, you're not paying the bills, Lane.
GM: Wait, wait. You dare to question the artistic integrity and vision of the architect?
Thorin: I would lo- I gotta have you guys up here. Did you play the game this weekend, or this last weekend?
GM: No, no, no, we're… it's the 26th we're playing this headache.
Thorin: I'd love to have you all up here sometime, like, I got, you know, some beds and stuff.
GM: No, I just, I just want you to know that,
GM: The reason I la- Grygum's been trying to say something, so why don't we let him say what he's been trying to say? Or did you… did you show something?
Grygum: Oh, I just… I pasted a photo of the couch that we bought into the general channel.
Thorin: Yeah, that is… I don't know the designers would be into that.
Grygum: So, should I…
GM: Given that we're all architects here, and very opinionated, and all handle people changing our systems in ways that we don't approve of long after we've let, and show a demonstrated, you know.
GM: you know, we exhibit none of those behaviors that Thorin described.
Grygum: Oh, never.
GM: Look, hold on, hold on.
Thorin: If they're paying me, and they're the paying the bills, then they get what they want. That's what I'm saying.
GM: Thorin, yes, I… okay, Thorin's a better man than I am. But I do want to share with you… I do want to share with you an amusing story from a different context. So my father is the great man of intensive care medicine.
GM: And there is an architect, a very famous architect.
GM: I can't remember his name now, but he's very famous. The guy who dealt… he's done, like.
GM: things all over the world, right? And so, the Niar House Foundation, which donates about $500 million a year, decided they were going to build a state-of-the-art research hospital in Thessaloniki.
GM: And so, they decide to hire this architect, because he's done a bunch of other work for them, he's a, you know, brilliant guy, and, you know, as every architect is, he looks at every design of every hospital ever made in disguises that he knows better.
GM: Right?
GM: Yeah, so…
Grygum: Don't we do this with every software.
GM: Yeah, I know.
GM: Yeah, I mean, there's…
Thorin: My weekend project was doing a new UI framework, by the way, you know, so, you know…
GM: So he knew better, right? So he shows up, and he just… so if you know anything about hospitals, they basically look like this. There's a core, there's a central area where all the surgery and the machinery is, and sitting around it is the hospital rooms.
GM: Right? Why? So that there's very fast, efficient, you can move the patient from their room to wherever they need to be very quickly. It makes everything just well-organized and a well-oiled machine.
Thorin: Let me guess, pneumatic tubes.
GM: No, he declared… he declared that that model was wrong.
GM: You know, so every hospital on the planet was, you know, he decided to redesign it. Now, my father is… is… is… let me just say that compared to my father, I have… I'm a pushover.
GM: I'm trying to imagine.
Thorin: this.
GM: I'm unopinionated. Like, I… I'm accommodating like hell, right? And so…
GM: my father's work… so he's got… so you've got this Titanic architect ego and my dad's ego in the room, and they're arguing, right? And this goes on for about 2 years, with hundreds of millions and billions of dollars at stake, as these hospitals need to be built, right?
GM: I mean, it… and so there was, like, all sorts of endless debates, because, you know, my dad cared about the functional elements of the hospital, and the architect cared about his aesthetic vision.
GM: And so there was, like, endless, endless wrangling over whether the door would be on the left or the right side.
GM: The arguments over the windows. So when you said, you know, an architect and you were arguing over things, man, I've just spent, like, the last 5 years of my life. Every other conversation with my dad has been about Renzo Piano, that's the name. Renzo Piano.
GM: And, the architects. And so, yes, I was being sarcastic, because I'm like, really? An architect who… because at one point, what happened was that the guy built the rooms in such a way that to get somebody in an emergency from the ICU, they had to go through 3 stairs, 4 doorways, whatever, to get to the surgery.
Thorin: Pneumatic tubes.
GM: Yeah, and my dad's like, that won't work. And he's like, why?
Thorin: I mean, let's be honest, you go into a hospital, and you know you're in a hospital, and it's, like, immediately depressing.
Daz: Yeah.
GM: Yeah, no, yeah, I'm not… I'm not… yeah, so this is a… this is a modern… it is a… it is a modern… it is, I kid you not, a work of art.
GM: But, like, as someone who had to sit through the two egos arguing with themselves.
GM: Oh, here it is, here's the… here it is. Here, I'll show it to you.
Thorin: Oh yeah, I wanna see.
GM: Release soon.
Thorin: Can I just say the new laptops, because I have an M5, and I'm, like, on my M1 now, and this thing is, like, it's putting out some heat now.
Thorin: The new ones are more efficient.
GM: Alright, so, so… It's very pretty. I already, I can already see the points of the contention.
GM: So, you'll notice that he has 2 buildings.
GM: Yup. Not… not the one with the one pillar.
Grygum: It's got a courtyard.
GM: Yes, it's got a courtyard, it's got… it's, you know, it's got all of these aesthetics. And you'll notice this hallway over here. This hallway over here was, like, the source of endless outrage and discussion.
GM: Because they needed to move patients from Building A to Building B, and Renzo was, you take them downstairs, you move them across, and you move them up. Don't you dare sully my architectural vision!
GM: And my dad's like, you're gonna make the nurses drag things up and down here for days.
GM: So, yes. So anyway, this guy, this guy and my dad spent 5 years of my life arguing.
GM: I, I, I just…
GM: because my mom… my mom has Alzheimer's, and so my dad would normally… my mother would normally be the victim of my dad's endless complaining. But during COVID, he and I talked every day, so…
GM: I would have to listen to the endless debates about Renzo Piano, and how Renzo Piano does not listen, and what do I think about architects who blah blah blah, and you know, I'm just kind of, like, going…
GM: Yes, yes, I… all the architects I work with are like Thorin. They do what the customer wants.
Zalthir: Early.
GM: Meanwhile, the president of the Nieros Foundation is, like, going, I was able to shut down a hospital in Greece. Like, shutting down a hospital in Greece is… public hospital is a big deal, because you're firing a whole bunch of people, right? And so, it's a government employee's, and we don't do that in Greece, right?
GM: And so, he's like, I've managed to shut down a hospital, but I can't build one because these two egotists can't agree on the location of the window.
Grygum: I remember someone telling me that in Greece, if you need blood, then you have to go find people to donate it to you.
GM: You know, it's not that bad. It used to be that bad, but it's.
Grygum: Oh, okay.
GM: Yeah, it used to be that bad. It used to be that bad, but no, no, we've… things have changed a lot since then.
GM: But yes, I just… I just wanted you to know that that was, you know.
GM: Yes, the building with the hallway. That's… I can't look at this without thinking of the five… my dad, like, throwing a temper tantrum. And poor Enzo Piano… poor Enzo Piano was kind of, like, the token guy my dad would get pissed off at, because he had, like, my mom was sick and all his whole life, and so Renzo Piano would, like, receive the full diatribe.
Grygum: Well, whatever you say about someone named Piano, at least they're quiet, right?
GM: Yes, exactly. Alright.
GM: Let us begin.
Thorin: Are we gonna kick some ass today?
Thorin: Are we gonna roll.
GM: furnished.
Thorin: F.
GM: You were falling.
Zalthir: Right.
Thorin: Oh, yeah.
GM: Like, just to be clear, we are gonna roll for initiative, but I don't think you're gonna like the result.
Grygum: Well, no.
Thorin: I'm trying to remember, because I got outs. I don't remember where we were.
GM: I will, I will read, I will read.
Thorin: I used my outs and I lost. I don't remember what I did. It was bad.
GM: Yeah, it was bad. I mean, just so we're on the same page, it was bad. Bad things happened to you, my friend.
GM: But yes, there should be comment this session.
GM: I've, I've prepared that. Let me just go…
GM: Okay.
GM: With the battle and the High Tower finally over, the party secured, A'lai Aivenmore and stripped him of his key to the Inner Sanctum, giving it to Glabbagool.
GM: Broken and desperate, A'lai offered the party something everything had left. He revealed the existence of a secret room beneath Candlekeep, holding artifacts of extraordinary power, guarded by a cryptogram he had spent years quietly researching.
GM: He knew the answer to two of its redditals, Fustilugs, the based insult, magically enchanted centuries ago under one of the oversized black marble chess pieces.
GM: And… a bow, the reply of the legendary halfling bard Batbayar's statue.
GM: When, when A'lai one night had applauded Batbayar, and the bow was the reply, yeah, okay, so the party regrouped in the investigator's office, where A'lai Aivenmore, whose photographic memory allowed him to reproduce the cryptogram in full, spread the riddle across the floor for every sharp mind in the room to examine.
GM: Sylvira Savikas arrived shortly after, grateful for the party's efforts and eager to help Candlekeep in this moment of crisis, though too weak from her illness to act herself, and still unaware that her son Moziqodo lay dead by the party's hand. She laughed at the riddles as almost too easy, provided the true name of Miirym, the Sentinel Wyrm, and the dragon guardian of Candlekeep.
GM: This is important. As to the answer to the first riddle, and identified the eastern light of Mystra's Mantle, Limniz, as an obscure star recorded in the charts of the Orrery of the Astronomicon, though she noted with quite unease that three unfamiliar figures had been seen inside the orrery when she passed it. Working together, the party decoded the later substitution cipher of the cryptogram.
GM: With Thorin leading the effort, with an assist from a cryptogram
GM: sight, and a lively argument over whether certain glyphs were an I or a J, to the stunned admiration of every scholar in the room.
GM: Grygum, solving in parallel, supplied the one line Thorin had missed. The full text revealed a sequence of instructions. Feed the quill of Alaundo the seer, tread as many steps as he lived in years, utter the original prophecy to unseen ears… unseen ears. I'm gonna just copy and paste this so you guys have it.
GM: Sprinkle dust of Mechanus on dormant gears, one last guardian of knowledge remains to verify the chosen reader's claims. And those well-versed in Candlekeep's lore may fearlessly pass the obsidian door. Alright.
Grygum: Hey,
GM: I'm gonna put this in the chat.
Grygum: didn't, I think we should have had a little more fear.
GM: What do you mean?
GM: Oh, okay.
GM: Blah blah blah, Kalan Strongbranch arrived huffing and puffing moments later, eager to contribute a clue he had solved, only to find the party had already cracked the entire cipher, leaving him to recover his composure and insist on being useful anyway by identifying the statue of Alaundo in the Founders Court.
GM: The party made their way to the Founders Court and the House of Alaundo, where a great brass statue of the ancient seerr stood upon a dais, bearing a quill in an empty ink pot, worn smooth by centuries of superstitious scholars touching it for luck.
GM: The superstition being that touching the quill guarantees a well-critiqued piece of academia. After a brief debate over whether inkblood or the poisoned ink sample was the appropriate
GM: offering, I'm actually not actually evil, so I'm going to start with ink. The party borrowed from ink from the assembled scholars and poured it into this ink statue's ink pot. The dais ground forward with a deep mechanical groan, revealing a long, unlit staircase descending into the darkness below. Thorin's observation.
GM: Thorin's observation.
Thorin: What did I observe? I don't remember.
GM: Thorin's obviously…
Thorin: 5 minutes ago.
GM: Yeah, I know.
Grygum: Okay.
GM: Thorin's observation that in all those centuries nobody had thought to put ink in the pot drew looks of horror from the scholars. Why would anyone deface the thing? To know how many steps to count, the party needed to know how long Alaundo lived, a fact nobody present knew.
Grygum: One of the problems with this, with all these scholars is that there apparently are no young students around to cause trouble.
GM: And so, rather than hunting down the biography Alaundo the Wonder Years and the Hall of Momentous Deeds, they drove… traveled to the grove where Candlekeep's keepers of tomes were buried, finding his grave and learning he had died at the age of 97.
GM: The prophecy provided by the scholars, who knew it by heart, the party still needed one final ingredient, dust of Mechanus, required to sprinkle on the dormant gears described in the riddle. They made their way to the House of Mechanus, a rectangular building with a blue roof and a clock tower, where the gnome librarian, Spanner.
GM: Sometimes, I wonder at DnD module writers and their names. Oversight!
GM: oversaw 13 Modrons, strange box-like mechanical creatures from the plains of Mechanus and their precise and orderly work, sort of like an OCD's person's wet dream.
GM: Spanner explained that the dust was the most perfect lubricant in existence, and that the only way to obtain it were to kill one of his Modrons. Absolutely unacceptable, and the party agreed. We don't kill librarians. They are our friends.
GM: already used the specialized tools his Modrons had crafted. Spanner wanted collateral. Thorin pointed out that they only needed the dust, not the tools. The party persuaded Spanner to lend them the tools, and he agreed on the condition that Zalthir and Glabbagool remain behind for a study of their mechanical symmetry, an interview Zalthir accepted on the condition of constructed
GM: Constructive feedbacks.
GM: deferred until after the descent. The Modrons then performed a strange synchronized dance as they deliberated amongst themselves in a language no one else in the room could begin to understand.
GM: Armed at last with everything they needed, the party descended the hidden staircase beneath Alaundo's statue, counting each step carefully toward the 97th. Daz positioned himself higher on the stairs for a clear line of sight, while the others spread out below. Grygum pouring 40 points of healing into Zalthir, who was 27 points with no short rest taken.
GM: Thorin, suspicious of the GM's repeated questions about exactly
GM: Thorin, suspicious of the GM's repeated questions about exact positions, was proved right. Without warning, a 10-foot section of the staircase hinged open beneath their feet, catching everyone standing between the 93rd and 102nd steps, Daz safely above, cast
GM: Telekinesis to arrest the fall. Everyone but Thorin caught hold of the stairs and scrambled clear. But Thorin lost his footing entirely and plummeted downward into the vast, circular well below, his fate uncertain.
GM: As the darkness swallowed him whole.
GM: Alright.
Daz: Mirth.
GM: Just to recall, you also have, you also… it wasn't in the summary, but you've also taken, one of the, avowed that's coming with you, you know, as a researcher and all things…
Grygum: Alright, we wanted somebody who is an expert on the history of Candlekeep.
GM: Yes, and it turns out there was somebody there, and as you correctly pointed out, he was, you know, not… he wasn't one of the well-known scholars.
GM: Right, I mean, who studies the history of a university? Only the, you know, scholar who does that.
Grygum: Top scholars, but the ones who…
Thorin: Very, meta.
Grygum: to you when you ask.
GM: Yeah. But this is that one time when, you know, it's kind of like that one time when the dermatologist gets called to the ER.
Thorin: And you laugh, but, like, when my wife had that sinus thing, there was, like, an ENT that had to come in and, like, Roto-Rooter her sinuses as an emergent thing, because it was, like, a serious infection. She was, like, technically septic, so, you know…
Daz: Oh, wow.
GM: I didn't say… I didn't say it doesn't happen.
Thorin: I know, but it is rare, yeah.
Grygum: They don't… they don't have one as… they don't have a resident in the ER who specializes.
Thorin: No, no, it's not like they're living there, yeah.
GM: There's a… there's a great TV show called Scrubs, where it shows, like, the ER doctor, the…
GM: the dermatologist running to the ER, right, you know, like, acting like, dermatology emergency!
GM: Alright, okay, so you are falling.
GM: That is your problem.
Grygum: And I think I had already checked to see if I have anything that I can do about that. Let me…
Grygum: Let me look one more time, though.
Grygum: It's not on my regular spell list.
GM: Alright.
GM: So…
Grygum: This gust of wind wouldn't help.
GM: Alright.
GM: Okay, so…
Grygum: Nothing.
GM: You have nothing.
GM: Okay, so, Zalthir has fallen.
GM: So, Zalthir keeps falling. He's falling into the dark.
Thorin: here.
GM: Great,
Thorin: Storing.
GM: Thorin. Thorin fell. Sorry, sorry, Zalthir, sorry.
Zalthir: I thought I was gonna grab him or something, like…
GM: What happened was that Thorin fell through, and then… What's his name?
GM: Pulled up the… used telekinesis to move it… close the gate.
Zalthir: Close it, or just kind of stop it from going all the way down?
GM: Stop it from going all the way down. So you're gonna rush after him, is that your plan?
Zalthir: I mean, I could fly, sure, why not?
GM: By the way, this came up. How can you fly?
GM: Your 9th level, Dragonborn can fly?
Zalthir: My first level dragon, [inaudible].
GM: Oh, really?
Zalthir: [inaudible]
Zalthir: That is my recollection. Let's see…
GM: I'm happy to have that ruling, I just want… I just… my… my AI systems were all screaming, he can't fly. I'm like, yes.
GM: Canonically, Zalthir's characters fly.
Zalthir: It's a rule, it's a house rule.
Thorin: Dang.
GM: Yeah, canonically, Zalthir's characters fly, and if they can't, they immediately find an artifact that allows them to fly, so we can just skip the…
Zalthir: I mean…
GM: I don't… I mean, whatever. Okay.
Zalthir: Let me, let me research while you continue.
GM: Yes, alright.
GM: Okay, well, no, we need to know what you're… so, we'll assume you're flying. Either you drank a potion of flying, or you're flying with your… you're flapping with your wings.
Zalthir: Do you have a potion of Flying, worst case.
GM: Yes, so one way or the other, you're flying. Alright. Glabbagool is screaming, WEE! Meanwhile, Dawnbringer is going, NOT THIS AGAIN!
GM: As you're falling down into the darkness.
GM: Alright, Zalthir here, what are you doing? You're racing after him?
Zalthir: Okay, that… okay, that worked. I put the action in, roll 20. Oh, it's level 5.
GM: Oh, okay, it was level 5, right? Okay, so that's fine.
Thorin: I'm gonna assume that I used all the, like, potential outs that I could have had.
GM: Yeah, yeah, yeah, I mean, I think there were, like, outstanding…
Thorin: Did you get a luck point?
GM: Yeah, I used them all.
Thorin: And I just had, like, a series of really shitty rolls.
GM: Yes, yes, I believe we were all staring at these shitty rolls in awe.
Grygum: Yeah.
Daz: It was only, like, ones and twos and stuff.
GM: Yeah, it was, it was…
Daz: For all of us.
GM: Yeah, I was just like… It's, like, pretty impressive.
Zalthir: Okay, so, yes, I'm flying, and I am ridiculously fast, so… I don't know how…
Zalthir: I assume I can catch up to him.
GM: Well, I mean, you know, this is where I have to look up the rules.
GM: How fast does a character fall in 5th edition?
Grygum: Are… are you trying to say you can fall faster than him?
Daz: Is it a… is it a…
GM: No, no, no, no, I'm just like, what is the…
Zalthir: So I can walk… rather, I can fly at my walking speed, and my walking speed is fast, and then I can do, like, triple speed walking.
GM: No, no, dude, no, I, I, no, I, I, okay.
Zalthir: Oh, and I can teleport! I forgot about that, yes.
GM: Alright, oh, okay, okay, turns out you fall okay. In Dungeons & Dragons, an optional rule from Xanathar's Guide to Everything states that a character falls 500 feet in a 6-second round.
Zalthir: 500 feet in 6 seconds.
Daz: Is it… But is he… is it, like…
Daz: the same speed as the European or the African?
Grygum: So…
GM: So, strictly speaking, you're faster if you don't try to fly down, but just fall.
Grygum: 500 feet, or only.
GM: So, Zalthir, here's what I'm willing to do. Zalthir, here's what I'm willing to do.
GM: Alright? He falls down 500 feet, you realizing that flapping your wings down isn't gonna catch it, decide to plummet along with him.
Zalthir: Err, how dark is it?
GM: Dark.
Zalthir: Okay, can I just shadow step to him?
GM: Well, I mean, given that he fell 500 feet… yeah, you can, like, once you get down at around 500 feet, you can shadow step to him, you can fly to him.
GM: I'm just gonna assume that at some point in time, you guys are… like, after… you're at the.
Zalthir: Okay.
GM: book.
Zalthir: For what it's worth, my plan was to immediately fall with him. So, like, I assume we're about at the same height regardless.
GM: Right, right, right. So yeah, so yeah, that's what I'm saying. You can't catch up with him as he's falling, but you can definitely catch up with him, because it turns out there's a… you've just fallen 500 feet, and you're still falling.
Grygum: That's really far.
Grygum: I… I think… Are any of us not falling?
GM: Yes, the rest of you, the rest of you managed to scramble, like, Daz is still using telekinesis to keep everything in place.
Zalthir: M…
Grygum: I am…
Zalthir: Go ahead and…
Grygum: watching. Wow, guys.
Zalthir: Go ahead and do something to slow his fall, like wind resistance, you know, I don't know.
GM: But you can catch him, like I'm saying, you can catch him.
Zalthir: Oh, oh, so I catch up. Okay, so I can grab him.
GM: Yeah, no, I'm just saying that…
Grygum: I don't have…
GM: The point is you catch up at 500 feet, you don't catch up at the very top. That's the thing that.
Zalthir: Understood. Yeah, we're way down, but he's not falling anymore, or at least…
GM: No, no, no, he's, like, holding onto you, giving you a hug, and you're, like… and Glabbagool is, like, saying one should always be Zen.
Zalthir: Yes, we're very… we're very zen at the moment.
GM: Yeah, and it's like, you know, Glabbagool's also wondering, is this too much hugging?
Zalthir: There are worse things about Google.
Thorin: GM, am I dead?
GM: No, no, no, you're… canonically, you, like, you're grabbed, you've grabbed Zalthir, and Glabbagool's asking if there's too much hugging.
Thorin: I mean, Glabbagool's all about the hugging, let's be clear.
Zalthir: Right.
GM: He's all about.
Thorin: a little bit.
GM: Who's doing…
Thorin: in your space, as far as I know.
GM: It's all about the oozing.
GM: I was like.
Thorin: What is this oozing without being ooze?
GM: Like, you know, alright, so you catch up with him. Now, okay, so there's still another 500 feet to go. Would you want to go explore what's down, or do you want to go up?
Zalthir: I mean, I think the point was to go down, wasn't it?
GM: was?
Zalthir: How about we go gracefully down and just see what's there?
Grygum: Hey, you guys okay down there?
Zalthir: So far.
GM: Thorin, what do you respond with?
Thorin: I'm like, I'm still kicking!
GM: Alright.
GM: the, of the avowed, the avowed, that you've dragged around is, look, raises an eyebrow. Come back!
Grygum: up for us!
GM: Or do you want… so are you going down? Is that what I'm hearing?
Zalthir: I mean, I… We're already halfway down, like…
GM: Right.
Zalthir: We could at least go scout a bit.
GM: Alright.
GM: So, down we go, we keep going.
Thorin: Sounds good.
GM: Alright.
GM: Alright, so you fall as… you drop another thousand feet, 500 feet, and then you hit a featherfall zone.
Zalthir: Oh.
Zalthir: So there was no danger here.
GM: Nope, I just, you know…
Grygum: Phew.
GM: So I guess you shout to everybody.
Zalthir: Yeah. Right.
Grygum: Oh, God, that's gonna be hard for me.
Zalthir: Literally? Like, should someone push you, or…
Grygum: Yeah, I might… Oh, y-you know,
Grygum: I'll just say a quick prayer, and I don't know… Take it from me.
GM: there.
Zalthir: Yeah.
Thorin: Boom.
GM: Alright.
Grygum: And… and hope that the featherfall works for me, too.
GM: Yes, so you, you all fall down. Daz, I presume you also, jump.
Daz: Yeah, I mean, I don't want to get split from the party.
Daz: My whole, like, trying to hold the thing up and save us all didn't work, so…
Grygum: If all your friends jumped off the stairs, would you?
Daz: Yeah.
Zalthir: Oh, shit.
GM: I mean… That… isn't that the whole point of adventure?
Grygum: Just to be…
Zalthir: Clear, though, do the 50 scholars behind us jump too, or do they hang out up there?
GM: No, no, the most… all but all one of the scholars is with you.
Grygum: Yeah, I think only one came before.
Thorin: Delicious.
Zalthir: Okay.
GM: Well, I mean, wait, he's like, I'm the scholar of… I'm the historical scholar of, of, whatchamacallit? Candlekeep, sorry, that was not… that was me.
Zalthir: I hope he forgot. Okay.
GM: I've, you know, this is… this is an area that has been, you know, I didn't even know it existed.
Thorin: Come on in, the water's fine.
GM: And he's going, I intend to write a very long monograph.
GM: I'm beginning to sense that monographs are the thing that everybody likes to write here.
Grygum: Alright. Yup.
GM: Alright.
GM: So, you land on a single tunnel which leads straight ahead.
GM: Okay.
GM: All right. This single passage leads to a huge… okay, let me just… I'm going to…
GM: Draw on a new map so that you guys don't get confused.
GM: Because I know… I know, I know this group is very…
GM: You know, can I just say something? This product used to be easy to use, and then the enterprise took over, and now it's become, like, a pain in the ass, and it's got 100 features. I'm trying to remember where everything was. You know, and I'm now looking for a simpler version… sorry, I'm just…
Grygum: I know a lot of people who use, what is it, Owlbear?
GM: Yeah, no, there's… there's lots of different tools, but… but I'm just… I'm just being… I'm just being silly. Like, every time I use a product, I'm like, oh god, you know, this is the downside of AI.
GM: Alright.
GM: Okay.
GM: You should see a blank screen. Are you on a blank screen? Yes, you are.
Grygum: I do see a blank screen.
GM: Alright.
GM: So…
Grygum: I assume it's blank because we're 1500 feet below the camera.
GM: Yeah, the single passage leads to a huge cylindrical cavern, some 200 feet high and 100 feet across.
GM: And the players, you find yourselves entering the cavern.
GM: halfway up this chamber. The cavern air is thick.
GM: Acrid and sweltering, hot and looking down from the small ledge that juts from the passage into the cavern.
GM: You behold a steaming lake of molten lava some hundred feet below. Alright, so let me see if I can draw this…
GM: Okay, so it's… 200 feet high and 100 feet across.
GM: So…
GM: Let me see if I can draw this. So, this is the bottom, alright? The blot, and so we'll just draw red to indicate lava.
Thorin: You have, like, millions of dollars to GPUs at the touch of your fingers, and you're, like, scribbling.
GM: Yes!
Thorin: Love it. Go analog, man.
GM: Dude, you know what? The technology, the world's technology, alright. And so…
GM: This is the top of it, alright?
GM: Okay.
GM: This is 200 feet.
GM: And, you guys appear on a ledge.
GM: I'm just gonna use a purple line so it's obvious.
GM: Okay, except that it's using the wrong tool.
Grygum: And that 200 feet is up and down, right?
GM: Yeah, it's like, you arrive… you are at 100 feet.
Grygum: And we're on the purple line?
GM: Yes, and you are on the purple line.
GM: Then we'll place the party.
GM: And you're on the purple line.
GM: So this is what the situation looks like.
GM: Alright, directly ahead in the center of the chamber is a three-floor
GM: A three-floor stone tower, similar in style to some of the older spires in the Great Library.
GM: Alright, so there is a 3 towers, there's a spire, there's a tower, right, so… 4-1… Floor 2.
GM: Lore 3. Basically.
Grygum: in the light lava? Yes.
GM: Yes, but it's, of course, not in the lava, because, you know, whoever wrote the module realized that somebody would observe that, is it in the lava? So why isn't it melting?
Grygum: Well, I mean, it's DnD, so the answer is magic.
GM: No, no, it's… have you not read the Candlekeep archive?
Grygum: I guess I'm not… I have not read all of the canon.
GM: Yeah? No, sorry. Okay. Directly ahead in the center of the chamber is a three-floor stone tower similar in style to some of the older spires in the Great Library, as your avowed guy says. Oh, yes! This is a classic example, and he starts spewing.
GM: of the architectural style invented by the Candlekeep [inaudible] architect. Many of these samples have been destroyed as a result of needless rehabilitation and expansion of towers as we fought for a constrained space in the library.
GM: This, in and of itself, was worth the trip.
Daz: I'm pretty sure there are some spells that allow you to, like, listen to what somebody's saying from across the room. They need to have spells that allow you to just mute people around you.
Daz: Or, like, zapping it, you know?
Daz: Mixer board for everybody that's standing around you.
GM: You could totally.
Thorin: It's like a remote, you can, like, turn somebody down.
Daz: Yeah, yeah, just…
Grygum: You know, Discord has that for, if you use the Discord chat feature, you can pop people down.
Daz: Yeah.
GM: Okay, the tower is mounted on a thin pedestal made of glassy black obsidian that soars from the pool of lava, while a double door of the same material
GM: stands opposite you, but 30 feet away with no obvious way of getting there. Well, I mean, not if this… not with this group. The base of the tower is surrounded by a narrow walkway, and on the opposite side of the walkway, a flat stone bridge leads from the back of the tower to a second tunnel opposite the one you came down.
GM: Alright.
GM: So… There's another… let me just see if I got this right.
Grygum: There's… there's a tunnel out of the top layer of the layer cake there.
GM: Alright,
GM: The base of the terrace around a banana walkway, and on the opposite side of the walkway, a flat stone bridge leads from the back of the tower to a second tunnel opposite the ones you came down. Alright, so there's another, sort of…
GM: Walkway over here.
GM: Sorry.
GM: This should be purple.
Grygum: And we'd… we'd have to figure out how to get over to it somehow.
GM: Yes, I mean, but with this party, that should be…
Grygum: This reminds me of an old, you know, sort of platform jumper video game.
GM: Yes.
GM: Okay, the ledge you find yourselves on extends just 5 feet into the cavern, and features several cogs and mechanical components embedded in the stone.
Daz: Are mechanical components embedded in the stone?
GM: Yes.
GM: So, this is where, you know, remember, you were looking for mechanist dust.
GM: So, you can try…
Grygum: Got it with us. Okay.
GM: Yeah, so you have the… don't forget, you have the mechanist tool, so you can try using that.
Grygum: So, I think it would be worthwhile looking at the mechanical components. Any idea what they're for?
GM: Well, so, roll an investigation.
Grygum: Sure.
Thorin: All of us, or just,
GM: Well, then there's Daz, then there's Daz.
Daz: Investigation… yeah, my passive investigation is, 24, and I roll with advantage, so let's see what happens.
Daz: 18 and 13.
GM: So, 31?
GM: Or is it… no.
Daz: No, two, it's… those were the two rolls, the 18 is the one that counts.
GM: Alright, so…
Daz: If my passive investigation is 24, then…
GM: Yeah, yeah, we've established that, you know, if you investigate something, you know, you go for full Sherlock Holmes.
Grygum: Yeah.
GM: All right. So, what you've uncovered is that this mechanical system is, in fact, a way to extend the bridge.
Daz: Oh.
Grygum: Oh, well, that would be more convenient than just trying to jump across the lava.
GM: Yes.
GM: So… You have to use the tool to do that.
Daz: So if we use the tool, we can basically expand the bridge. Yes, yes. And we don't have to… okay.
Grygum: Try it.
Daz: Let's do it.
GM: while you're,
GM: Looking at that, you realize it's fortunate that you brought the tool, because you notice a, a, you know, one of those, warning, kind of like, a plaque.
GM: That says that, warns,
GM: That this area, this entire airspace is surrounded by an anti-magic field.
Daz: Okay.
GM: So you couldn't just use magic to fly.
Grygum: Wasn't that supposed to be this whole, this whole central area?
Grygum: But I guess we… what we found out was that it was disabled anyway.
GM: Yeah, so no, this, there was a… there was a field, force field, that prevented teleportation and magic from coming in or out to Candlekeep. It also prevented fire from being cast.
Grygum: Fire, okay.
GM: Right.
Grygum: more general.
GM: Yeah, this is a… so this is sort of a general, let me just put it, anti-magic area.
GM: But, thanks to your clever use of the mechanical tool, you are able to… the bridge sort of grinds.
Daz: I really like the soundboard that,
Daz: That our GM uses for DnD.
Grygum: I don't know if that was a soundboard.
GM: Yay!
GM: It's called the Mark I vocal cord.
Daz: Yeah. That's a good one.
GM: Alright.
GM: Okay.
GM: Okay, so you arrive at…
GM: Okay, so you arrive at… the door opens, and you finally arrive at a dungeon. Alright.
GM: Just make sure.
GM: Hold on. I have the dungeon, but I forgot to get the version that has the numbers on it. Give me a second.
GM: Let me just… this will take all of one second.
GM: Of course, this is where DnD Beyond fails me.
GM: Right.
GM: Right. You arrive…
GM: Bring it.
GM: Alright, okay. I have the… I have the answer. Alright.
GM: So, let me just do this.
GM: Okay, we are… okay. Everything should be black right now, so… which is to be expected.
GM: And, polygon.
GM: Right.
Daz: We've fallen into darkness.
GM: now you haven't fallen into darkness. The darkness has fallen into you, kind of thing.
GM: So to… because, like, GM… I mean, I could… you could watch his… you could watch me struggle with technology, or we can just assert that you're now standing inside of a tower.
GM: And so this is… imagine… and so there's, like, multiple levels to this tower, but, like, I didn't…
GM: use all of the technologies that I have at my disposal. So there's a door. Would you like to open the door? I mean, after all, you've arrived at this tower, and whatever… and you know Manshoon has beaten you to this, so going through this door seems to be…
Grygum: Yes, I opened the door.
GM: Alright.
GM: As you, just as a side note, the tower's stone walls are unadorned except for several sconces, lit with continual flame spells.
GM: And four Mounted Crossbows.
GM: Alright.
GM: Okay, so you… okay, so you enter this chamber.
GM: Night.
GM: Okay, so, you enter the chamber. We will be using the orange markers for the map squares, not the under… the gritty thing underneath.
GM: Okay, so let me see what happens over here.
GM: As soon as you enter the guard… enter the chamber.
GM: Who's our name?
GM: Very interesting.
Thorin: Nothing happens, right?
GM: No, no, no, no, nothing happens.
Grygum: As soon as you enter the chamber, nothing happens.
GM: no, no, no, no, I'm now… I've lost my… I lost my sight. There we go. Okay.
GM: Alright, okay, so we're not there yet. Okay, so you arrive in this, in this area, alright?
GM: As you enter… Okay, blah blah blah…
GM: The only room's only noteworthy feature is a tiny iron statue of what looks like a winged owlbear that sits atop an 8-foot-high stone pedestal. A staircase runs behind the pedestal up to the next floor of the tower.
GM: Alright?
GM: As soon as you enter the… as soon as you enter the guardian, which I guess is the owlbear, iron statue's large eyelids open to reveal white, glowing eyes, while its wing unfolds, and it flies directly up and hovers 12 feet above the ground.
GM: Alright.
GM: Halt Seekers! Before you consult the mysteries stored herein, you must prove yourselves a worthy keeper of secrets. Three questions you must answer before I let you pass.
GM: Fortunately, you brought yourself…
Thorin: Tip-top A-plus DnD right here.
Grygum: Is that right?
Thorin: Questions 3 you must answer.
GM: Yes, three questions you must answer. Not two, not one, not zero. If thou shalt answer zero, one, or two, bad things shall happen.
Daz: Alright.
GM: Alright.
GM: Where is the only refuge for flames in Candlekeep?
GM: so…
Daz: Do we know that from that, from that, word puzzle thing that we had?
Grygum: Oh, ye…
Zalthir: Was it on there?
Daz: Everybody write down the text for that?
GM: So, so,
Thorin: No.
GM: So, so just, just as a side note, if you roll a nominal, let's say, history check.
Thorin: I know you told us about this at one point, but I don't remember.
GM: Yeah, yeah, that's fine.
Daz: Yeah, I'm a parent.
Thorin: Currently not the one.
GM: I mean, fortunately, Daz remembers the one place where you can have fire, which is the hearth, because that was the only place he wasn't cold.
Daz: Oh…
Grygum: Yeah, okay, I got a 13.
Daz: work.
GM: Yes, yes.
GM: Well done! Well done! Well done! The avowed… the avowed guy who's coming in… I knew the ques… I knew the answer to that.
GM: But, but, but, you know, it's…
GM: He goes, if you're going to answer the questions, I'm going to just… over here.
GM: Alright, then he goes. Now comes the second question.
GM: Which holy, triumvirate patron, the great library! Alright, roll in a religion check.
Grygum: Oh, I'm good at that.
GM: Yes.
Grygum: 19. Oh, no, 20.
Zalthir: I hate mine. You're even better.
GM: Oh my god, did you really…
Thorin: Three!
Thorin: With my plus 2.
GM: Thorin…
Daz: 13.
GM: Choosing… are you choosing to be quiet in this… in this sense?
Thorin: I got nothing to add.
GM: Okay, I'm just, just asking, right? Okay. So, Grygum, you, of course, remember who it was. It was Oghma, Deneir, and Milil.
Grygum: Of course I remember that.
GM: Of course you remember that, and you know, you barely resist the temptation to explain exactly how they founded Candlekeep, etc, etc.
GM: Alright.
GM: Alright, the third question, and this is the most difficult of all the questions.
Grygum: -Oh.
GM: Once upon a time… Every member… oh, sorry.
Thorin: Comment and a question.
GM: No, no, that was, that was, you know, that was…
GM: The owlbear goes, sorry, sorry, I was reading from the answer key, my mistake.
Thorin: My mouth shut.
GM: It's been a while, it's been a while, it's been a while, but don't you worry, if you fail, I will tear you to shreds and destroy you. I've been waiting a long time for this…
Thorin: No less, yeah.
GM: I've been waiting a long time to do this. This is something I have trained for in my head.
Grygum: That would be no less than your duty.
GM: Exactly. I was built for this!
GM: How many feet does the High Tower of Exaltation reach above the sea?
Zalthir: Would we know that?
Thorin: I mean.
Zalthir: And one of the dots.
Thorin: With us doesn't know it.
Zalthir: Yeah.
GM: What?
Thorin: We got, like, all the scholars with us, right?
GM: No, no, you got the One Scholar.
Zalthir: Yeah, but this Candlekeep scholar, like, he would.
GM: Yeah, yeah, no, I'm just, I'm just, I'm just, I'm just…
Thorin: So we stare at him.
Grygum: What's his name?
GM: What's his name?
Thorin: We stare at what's his name.
GM: Sorry, I do not have it, I do not have his name right now. Alright, he's staring, he,
Grygum: I've got all the difficult questions.
GM: No, no, I have… I have a book.
GM: It has names. You don't think I was gonna, like, what?
GM: I have many books. Alright.
GM: He goes, Edvaldo Sedanur.
Grygum: Evaldo, this seems like the sort of question that you would know the answer to.
GM: Well, you know, this was one of those things, every member of the Avowed was expected to know the answer to this question.
Thorin: Apparently, there.
Daz: I'm sure they all have a slightly different answer, maybe.
GM: No, no, no, no, no, but, you know, however, the practice of memorizing such dry details has long fallen out of fashion in Candlekeep.
Daz: So you guys don't know.
GM: Like, he goes, he goes, but, but I, I do have, I do have, I do have a, I, I do, I, I do know something.
GM: It's over 500 feet?
Grygum: It isn't some kind of trick like the, you know, like the tower is actually below sea level, or something like that, right?
GM: Right. So, because you brought the Avowed guy, normally the DC is an insane 23, I have reduced it to 16 nature check.
GM: So…
Grygum: Nature?
Zalthir: reasons.
GM: Yes, yes.
Thorin: Alright.
Daz: Boy!
Thorin: Yo.
GM: You, you, you got it?
Thorin: Hey, I've got a point.
Grygum: Good.
Daz: So did Thorin. Thorin and Daz.
GM: Alright, so Thorin and Daz, you are able to answer the question correctly, to which the owlbear goes.
GM: You have answered all three questions correctly. You may pass.
Daz: Cool.
Thorin: Could we have taken him?
Zalthir: I mean, I was tempted to just try anyway.
GM: Huh? Okay.
Zalthir: We want to, Thorin? Could be fun.
Thorin: you know, what you got on him?
Grygum: You could… you could still just attack him if he fell.
Thorin: But we don't know what's ahead. We don't want to, like, you know… This is the… this is the problem with DnD. You're always like, should I use this spell, or should I save it for later? And you never know.
Grygum: I mean, we can always… at this point, we can save doing something stupid for later.
GM: Nope.
Zalthir: That's fair.
Zalthir: Maybe he'll stay here, in the worst case, get him on the way back.
Grygum: Where's that?
Thorin: So we can ask him, so, now that we've, answered your questions, what's next for you? Are you, are you done with your duties down here?
Thorin: When do you get off?
GM: Alright, hold on, I need to check something.
Grygum: Yeah, do you think these guys have shifts?
GM: Yeah, hold on.
GM: Okay.
GM: Although this was all very entertaining.
GM: Alright, as you're about to,
GM: As you're about to go upstairs, you hear a cough.
Daz: That's not the guy that just questioned us, somebody else.
GM: No, no, no.
Daz: Where's it coming from?
GM: From outside.
Daz: Okay.
Zalthir: Like, sorry, outside, like, where we came from, behind us?
GM: Yes, outside, from the lava chain… from where the lava is.
Zalthir: Can we see who's coughing?
GM: Yes, well, I mean, I presume… I'm just asking, do you go outside?
Zalthir: No, just turn around and look.
GM: Okay.
GM: She, You see a, a spectral silver dragon.
GM: The lava…
Grygum: That's cool.
GM: Going through her and coming out the other side.
Grygum: True.
Grygum: per… Through what part of her?
GM: who we're holding.
GM: Okay.
GM: One… and she asks one question, she's looking at you, and she's looking very grouchy.
Daz: Okay.
Grygum: I would be if lava was going through me, too.
GM: So, she says, Someone entered this chamber without being a reader.
Daz: Or would, like, a Candlekeep avowed or something? Is that what they're upset about?
GM: NO!
Daz: A reader of what?
GM: He goes, so one of you.
Daz: I have my copy of Milo's Adventures on Reddit.
Grygum: Pointed as a reader or something?
Daz: like, I'm a reader.
GM: Alright, so, she sits there, and she goes.
Grygum: You mean you're, like, 1500 feet below the Candlekeep, and you're worried about academic appointments?
GM: No, she goes, so, so, sorry, so I just want to make sure how I articulated.
GM: She says, Manshoon entered my keep.
Daz: Oh, the, that guy.
GM: Yes!
Grygum: We don't like him either.
Daz: Because the protections fell when he entered. Okay.
GM: Yes, he entered.
Daz: What room did they enter?
GM: He goes, he's still inside.
Daz: Interesting. Do you know where?
GM: No.
Daz: We would like to, remove them.
GM: You would?
Daz: That is part of our goal, yeah.
GM: Well, I'm glad to hear that.
Daz: Good.
GM: So, one of you… okay, she's… so while you're sitting there, you realize that she is one of the verses of… she is one of the verses of the…
GM: Poem.
Daz: One of the verses, oh, of the poem.
GM: Yes.
Grygum: Let me pull it back up.
Zalthir: One aspect…
Thorin: To verify the chosen reader's claims.
Thorin: But those well-versed in Candlekeep's lore may fearlessly pass the obsidian door.
GM: Right.
Grygum: Is… oh, is… Have we already seen an obsidian door? Is there one here?
GM: Yeah, yeah, that's the one you just walked through.
Grygum: Oh, okay.
GM: Right.
Zalthir: So which one is she, then?
GM: She… she is the unseen ears.
Zalthir: Oh, so she's the one who dropped the floor under us?
GM: Yes.
GM: Okay. Well, you said the, you said the magic words, right? She's the last line in that, in that verse.
Zalthir: She's seen now, so…
GM: Yes.
GM: So she asks, one of you is the reader, the rest of you are witness. Which is which? And say it in the right order.
Grygum: Oh, one of us read the, read the words.
Grygum: Yeah.
Thorin: Or is Reader, like, a,
Thorin: a title in the keep, right?
Grygum: But we read the words aloud, I think.
Zalthir: Someone did.
Grygum: I have a feeling it was me, but I don't remember for sure.
GM: It was you, actually.
Grygum: Alright, I am the reader.
Grygum: I can read it again if you'd like.
GM: So she then says, Tell me something about…
GM: Tell me something you know about Candlekeep.
Grygum: Well, we,
GM: You know about anything. You could pick anything, you know, you could talk about the Endless Chant, the books, like, just prove that you know something.
Grygum: Oh, yeah, I, I talk about, all of the, all the books that we've, we've, we've looked into, and, some of the, some of what we had to track down recently.
GM: She goes, So, she goes, very well, reader!
GM: She pauses and says, you may… Grant a request.
Zalthir: Wait.
Zalthir: So we'll get a request.
GM: Congrats.
Daz: Okay.
GM: She goes, and so the requests you can ask, Alright.
Grygum: Does she know anything about this whole murder mystery? There were some loose ends that we needed to tie up.
GM: Well, I mean, so, things you can ask her, right?
GM: You can ask her to hold the door. Nothing leaves…
GM: The whole area until she says so.
GM: Alright, so let me just write these down.
Zalthir: And we asked her to join the party.
GM: You can ask, she may say no.
Thorin: Did you ever fight the, the, the owlbear?
GM: No.
Thorin: Like, no, we grabbed lunch together.
GM: Like, she's like.
Daz: True.
Thorin: He's my bud, what are you talking about?
GM: Alright, so you can hold the door.
GM: She can fight, you can ask to fight behind us, fight beside us.
GM: You can, those are the things that she can do.
Thorin: Well, if the bad guy's already in there, right? Like, we don't need her to hold the door. Hold it against whom?
GM: Well, from leaving.
Thorin: Oh.
GM: Right, so he could escape, for example.
Grygum: Could, could she, join forces with us long enough to try to defeat, what, what, the guy who's down here before us?
GM: So you guys have to pick your question, so ask yourself.
Zalthir: I mean, GM did say, fight beside us, I think that was an option.
GM: Yeah, it was an option.
Thorin: Yeah, I think that's more useful than just standing there waiting, like, playing goalie, you know what I'm saying?
Grygum: I think so, too.
GM: Yup.
GM: So these are the three questions.
Grygum: We asked her to fight, fight beside us to, defeat the Interloper.
Zalthir: Wait, wait, sorry, hold on, what's that middle option?
Thorin: Are we all who say we are? Oh, is one of our party, like, not where they're supposed to be?
Zalthir: Are we a mimic? Like, what's it?
Grygum: Well, there is…
Thorin: The… the useless dude?
Grygum: Wait, what about…
Daz: Oh, is the useless dude the bad guy, maybe?
Daz: Or somebody replaced Glabbagool with a mimic?
GM: But…
Grygum: But don't we have some mystery about one of us? I'm trying to remember who.
GM: Yes, you've got Daz's mystery.
Zalthir: Boom.
Grygum: Maybe we could find out more about Daz's mystery.
Grygum: Oh, tell us what he took is interesting, too, because presumably he came down here for a reason.
Grygum: And we don't know why.
Zalthir: But she already said she doesn't know where he is. Would she know what he took?
Grygum: I mean, those are different questions. If you took something and left, I'm sure.
GM: So, the other thing… okay, there's one detail that I did not… I got wrong, so just to be clear.
GM: So…
GM: The, the, the, the anti-magic field, it doesn't extend full 30 feet, it extends only 10 feet.
Daz: Okay.
GM: So if you're looking at the bridge.
GM: It's only for the first 10 feet.
GM: And so Daz…
GM: Alright, so Daz notices that, so it was a 10 feet, I'm sorry, I got that wrong.
Daz: Still needed the bridge, but we, we have some magic at the edges.
GM: Right, right, so the first, the first time closest to the bridge are, are, not.
GM: And so she's, like, sitting there, waiting for one of you to ask something.
Daz: Do we need to figure out what we want to ask?
GM: Right.
GM: Okay, so, apparently… Okay, so apparently this.
Daz: Can we ask more than one? Is there a chance for us to…
GM: Hold on, so to make this a little bit more… okay, so, I'm sorry, okay, so…
GM: She looks at you very irritated, and she says.
GM: Well, since you don't know what to ask for, and it's been centuries since anyone came here.
GM: And you, you, she looks at Zalthir, look, the calculating type.
GM: And she looks at you, Daz, and goes… and you do look like as if you're always searching for an angle.
GM: And then, she can't help but notice Grygum as a cleric of Bahamut.
Grygum: Tis true.
GM: And she goes, and you are a cleric of the great god Bahamut, the platinum god who soars above all, and, you know…
Grygum: I dare not deny it.
GM: Yes, and you are… are you an orc? I can never remember.
Grygum: Yes.
GM: And an orc, no less.
Grygum: Well, the orcs have occasionally allied with the dragons.
GM: If you say so.
GM: You say so. Alright, so here's what she can do. She can hold the curtain.
GM: Which means she can widen the anti-magic band to 30 feet.
GM: for 10 minutes. So that's… Something, if you're gonna fight Manshoon, who's a wizard, that might be very useful.
Daz: That could be very, very true.
Thorin: It does sound very useful, yeah.
GM: Right.
GM: And, and she's… because, because Grygum is a cleric, she's now explaining it, because out of…
GM: She pauses and then pauses for a minute and says, Where do you stand on the question of the age?
Grygum: Yes, I'm, I founded a new school that holds that there are certain fixed points among which we may make our own paths.
Grygum: To his…
GM: When she paused, she goes, why, wisdom, wisdom truly flows from Bahamut into you, cleric of Bahamut.
Grygum: I, I feel truly inspired, right, okay.
GM: So…
Grygum: Witness the power of my God.
GM: Right.
GM: She pauses and contemplates. Alright, so you can hold the curtain, she can extend the anti-magic zone.
GM: She can prevent Manshoon from teleporting out of there.
GM: Right?
GM: You can ask him what he took.
GM: You can ask if everyone is who they say they are, and and she answers the question, to fight behind you. I was bound to be witness, not weapon. If I could have stopped him, I would have stopped him at dawn.
Daz: gone.
GM: Manshoon showed up.
Daz: Yeah.
GM: Great.
GM: So, he can't… she can't… the fight beside… beside us is out.
Zalthir: Oh.
GM: Right.
Daz: Okay.
GM: So, she's an observer.
GM: So…
Grygum: You know, this whole,
Grygum: anti-magic thing sounds terribly useful against a powerful wizard. As much as it inconveniences me, I'll just fight in other ways.
Daz: It inconveniences me, too, but…
Daz: Like, if it's a super powerful wizard, it's probably not a great idea for us to be going up.
Grygum: Absolutely.
Daz: Correctly.
Grygum: Yeah.
Daz: Can she shape the field so that… our…
GM: Oh, she can't, she can only extend it.
GM: So… But the downside is that Manshoon can escape, so that's the downside.
Zalthir: Well, controlling where people move is kind of my thing.
GM: There you go.
GM: Let him try.
Zalthir: Oh, snap.
GM: Alright.
Zalthir: But can we delay it so we can surprise.
GM: Yeah, yeah, she, yeah, she, yeah, she, yeah, you can.
GM: Right.
GM: Alright.
GM: Alright, so I, so you're gonna go with the, hold the curtain?
Grygum: Seems… Seems like a good idea.
GM: She smiles and says, well chosen! Well chosen!
GM: Well chosen.
GM: Right.
GM: Okay, so here we are. Okay, so…
GM: You now enter the second floor, I presume, yes?
GM: So, with that piece of information, you head back into the obsidian, into the library, and you notice on the floor, there is a broken… now that you've come in here, and you've managed to ignore the owlbear, you notice that there is a damaged owlbear on the floor.
GM: Manshoon apparently destroyed the owlbear, and a new owlbear.
Daz: Took his…
GM: Took his, took his spot.
GM: Alright, so you head upstairs, presumably.
GM: And…
Grygum: And the anti-magic goes all the way up? Is that the idea?
GM: Yeah. No, no, so the… yeah, so yes, the anti-magic. I have to…
GM: Check that for the moment, but just… let me… let me just… okay.
GM: Alright, so here we are.
GM: So here we are.
GM: Alright, at the top of the stair links the vault with the guardian chamber.
Grygum: I probably need more information.
GM: Yeah, no, just give me a second.
Daz: Alright.
GM: Right.
GM: Correct.
GM: Okay, so you walk upstairs.
GM: Alright.
GM: And what you see… is… A hundred dangerous tome. A hundred dangerous tome.
Grygum: Dangerous… book?
GM: Tomes, yes, tomes, tomes, tomes.
GM: And we're talking, like, every… every dangerous, magical tome you could possibly imagine.
GM: You also noticed that the door was opened.
GM: And the door reveals another plain circular room lit with continual flame, its windows sealed shut. In this room, a single bookcase is mounted against the eastern wall, while the desks and chair occupy the middle of the room.
GM: Okay, so… Let me, describe this.
GM: Alright, so… So, just imagine there's a bookshelf, bookshelf around here.
GM: Alright, there's a note on the desk written in somewhat archaic Common, which reads, This vault was built to contain Candlekeep's most dangerous secrets. Consult here what can benefit civilization, but leave the tomes on these shelves.
GM: Whilst the most holy, unholy knowledge can be used for good should circumstances lead you, keeper of secrets, to believe that such dogma might be grasped by foul hands, you will find the means to destroy the contents of this vault in the chamber above.
GM: The room contains around 100 or so of the most
GM: Powerful magic books you could possibly imagine.
Grygum: Oh, I'm very excited.
GM: Right.
GM: Hold on.
GM: You're very excited. That's very good that you're very excited.
GM: There are books, you, you, there are lots and lots and lots of, books.
GM: Pure.
GM: And you also notice
GM: You also notice Manshoon, who's sitting there reading, and he does not look up immediately.
GM: He looks at you and says, by all means, browse.
GM: Right? The trick is leaving with what you came for. Did you come for the book, or did you come for me?
Grygum: Indeed, we came for you, we did not know of the books.
Grygum: Alright.
GM: So… Alright.
GM: Alright, so… Okay. So, so,
GM: Okay, so he looks at you, and he says, you've come for me and not for the books?
Grygum: The books are but a bonus.
GM: He sighs.
GM: He sighs and says, He sighs, and we roll for initiative.
Daz: Oh, no.
Zalthir: That's an intense sigh!
Grygum: Yes, 3.
GM: He goes, he sighs, like, wizard.
Grygum: Wow.
Thorin: I rolled a 20!
Thorin: I got a 19.
GM: Alright, hold on, I need to… I need to get a mage icon.
Daz: highlight… yeah, so that I don't see the chart yet, but…
GM: Yeah, it's because I haven't, loaded it up, clicked on it yet.
GM: Hold on.
Daz: What?
Daz: 3. That's not great.
GM: So, I need…
Daz: And we're currently in the zone of no magic, or, magical stopping.
GM: No, you're… you're not… not inside… inside the… so, inside the tower, Magic Works.
Daz: Okay.
GM: Right? So it's… it's…
Daz: Just at the gate.
GM: Yeah, so it's just, obviously magic has to work, otherwise all these books would be destroyed.
Daz: Okay, good point, yeah.
GM: Right.
Grygum: I thought maybe they were just paused.
GM: No, no.
GM: Alright.
GM: Alright, so, hold on. So I need to,
GM: I need to, delete this guy. I need to put him back on.
GM: Okay? No, that's not what I wanted. You can do better.
GM: Delete.
GM: Hold on… New character.
GM: Complete… Alright.
GM: I paid for these icons. I'm going to have the pretty icons.
GM: Sorry, this is just, alright.
GM: Alright.
GM: Let me just see if I… I have…
GM: Alright, so we roll for initiative, yes?
Grygum: Oh, yes.
Zalthir: Green Ball now? Oh, no, there we go.
Grygum: Believe we all did.
GM: alright, so now roll for initiative, so whatever you rolled…
Thorin: 19. I'm not rolling again.
GM: Okay, Thorin, you got a 19.
GM: What did you roll Daz?
Daz: If you remember…
GM: If you remember it and you like it, you can tell me. Otherwise, you can re-roll.
Daz: I don't remember. I'm gonna re-roll.
Daz: 21.
GM: Alright.
Zalthir: We had to re-roll? Alright.
GM: Yeah, Daz, I don't remember… I screwed up the die rolling, so yes, you get to re-roll.
Zalthir: Huh? Better.
GM: Zalthir, what did you roll? What did you roll? 4… 17?
Zalthir: I'm already up there.
Grygum: I figured out how to add it myself.
GM: Okay. And, Grygum, you're a 3, right?
Grygum: Unfortunately.
GM: Nice.
GM: Okay, so…
Zalthir: Cool. Yeah, you can add yourself, that's neat. But then you can't remove yourself.
GM: Yeah, you can't?
GM: I'm gonna remove you now.
Grygum: If you click on your token and do add turn, then it adds it a zero, and you can edit it.
Zalthir: Yeah, you can add, I just don't see a way to remove, but that's fine.
GM: click on the… I think you can click on the icon itself in the little screen.
Thorin: do.
GM: It adds your…
Zalthir: Puts you on the tracker. Again.
Thorin: Sorry.
GM: No, that's funny.
Thorin: I had to do it.
Zalthir: That's exactly what I did.
Thorin: I'm sorry, it was a fun night to present.
GM: You told her.
Thorin: I have to tell you.
GM: Thorin there's a button to press. I know, right? Seriously, man.
GM: You told Thorin there was a button.
GM: I just need to,
GM: I just need to get the, sim… the…
GM: I need to get his stat block.
GM: Alright.
GM: Okay, I need to… I just… alright, so…
GM: Okay.
GM: So I can get his initiative.
GM: Oh, it'd be helpful if I took the right…
GM: Council.
GM: Of course, that would happen. Of course it would happen. Of course I would click the wrong button, causing things to have to reload.
GM: Sorry. Sorry, guys.
GM: Alright.
Grygum: After an experience like this, I'll never click on anything again.
GM: Okay.
GM: Alrighty…
GM: Okie dokie. So… Alright. So, his initiative, what's his initiative?
GM: Alright.
GM: I had his stat block here, where's his stat block? No, no advantage on the dexterity. All of that energy to find out that he just… it's a straight D20. Alright.
GM: 12. Alright.
GM: Change, let me set him.
GM: What am I doing? Add turn. Alright, engine. Alright, 12. Alright.
GM: Okay, so, let us begin. Let me also add… the, Re…
GM: Alright, so your little… your little guy is also here as well. Alright, Thorin, you're up first.
Thorin: Oh my goodness. Alright, so who are we fighting again? We're fighting…
Daz: Thorin's up, or I'm up?
GM: Whoever… oh, sorry, I was not looking. Daz, you're up.
Thorin: Daz, you do it.
Thorin: Have fun.
Daz: Let's see, I've already used my 5th level…
Daz: So he's a, like, high-level wizard, so if I cast something on him that's also.
GM: He's not just a high-level wizard. He is a legendary high-level wizard who has come back from the dead more times than you know, you know.
Grygum: So, before we really get into the fighting, I want to propose to him that, you know, there's a lot of valuable books in this room. It would be a shame to damage any of them. What if we, what if we moved into the other rooms so they'd be safer?
Daz: That's a good proposal. What does he say?
Grygum: Hmm.
Grygum: the…
GM: So that was so… it was done with such earnestness, right?
Daz: It deserves an inspiration point, in my opinion.
GM: That man deserves an inspiration point, like, alright, literally, I'm gonna have to roll it. I just can't. Okay, roll… roll your, your, your, roll with it.
Daz: Persuasion or something?
GM: persuasion, or performance, I don't care, whatever you want.
Grygum: 17.
GM: Is that with your bonus?
Grygum: What did you say with Advantage?
GM: Yes, yes.
Grygum: 22.
GM: Alright, that was the number you needed to roll.
Grygum: Hey, that rules.
GM: Manshoon goes…
Daz: drinking.
GM: Manshoon goes, Yes, you're correct. We should not damage these books, they are of priceless origin.
Grygum: Indeed, indeed.
GM: And he goes, and clearly, one of us will leave with the book they want.
Daz: Correct.
Grygum: Let's all just leave them here for now. We can come back after we kill you.
GM: Or I killed you.
Grygum: Or, yes, yes, I admit it is a possibility.
GM: He goes, well, why don't you go down ahead?
Grygum: Sure.
GM: Alright, so he goes downstairs. No, downstairs is all the way,
Zalthir: Good luck.
GM: On the left.
GM: Right.
Grygum: let's see here.
GM: Alright, altir, put you over here.
Zalthir: Yep.
GM: Alright. With Glabbagool.
GM: Alright.
Grygum: I'm more civilized this way.
GM: Far more civilized this way.
Thorin: Great, I missed that. We sent them all away?
Zalthir: No, no.
GM: Sure.
Zalthir: Convinced him to go downstairs so we don't damage the books.
Daz: Yeah, and
Thorin: We're all moving the fight, because, like, you know…
Daz: Yeah, now he's, in an area where…
GM: So just to be clear, the anti-magic shell is on the bridge, right?
GM: It's not in the tower.
Zalthir: Yeah, how far away is the bridge? Like, feet?
GM: There's the… that's where the British.
Zalthir: 10 feet, okay.
GM: Right, it starts literally… yeah, so we'll just say it starts there.
Zalthir: Yeah, so 10 feet, awesome.
GM: Okay.
GM: He's, like, very suspicious. Like, you all seem very eager, but, you know, destroying the books with magical spells.
GM: Causing glyphs of warding to explode, people to die, you know, this would be a disaster.
Zalthir: A reasonable request.
GM: Yeah, no, he's, like, he's thinking how civilized of you?
GM: I think. So, he squirted down…
GM: I presume you take positions, place yourselves wherever you want.
GM: And he, sort of arrives standing menacingly over… from the… standing menacingly over Daz, place yourself. Alright, he stops there.
GM: And says… What does he say? He says, Well!
GM: Now we have found a place to have the magical duel.
Daz: Yes, we have.
GM: Yes, we have.
GM: Alright.
GM: So, he looks at you, and there's kind of like that, you know, okay corral sort of…
Grygum: to preparing.
Daz: to draw.
GM: Yeah, like, kind of like…
Thorin: Like, okay, right.
GM: Yeah, okay, corral moment, right?
Zalthir: Where's the owlbear there?
GM: The owlbear is participating not in this combat, since his job… everybody has answered the ques… the previous guy killed him, and you answered the questions. His job was to…
GM: Make sure, you know, so the owlbear's just sitting there.
Zalthir: Okay. We don't have to worry about friendly fire, or fire…
GM: No, no, he's just, you know, he might flit around to avoid, you know, explosions, and might offer real-time commentary.
Zalthir: Cool, commentary, nice.
GM: He might offer color commentary. That's a pretty nasty hit by Manshoon.
GM: Alright, so he's standing, he's standing at the top of the library, you're standing, it stares, there's, like, the, the thing, let us begin.
Zalthir: Yeah, did the turn order go away?
GM: Oh, yes, I accidentally hit it.
GM: Hold on, I need to do one thing.
GM: Well, you guys, Daz, you go, I don't think I'm gonna…
Daz: Yeah, I'm trying to figure out what the best thing to try is, given they're a really high-level wizard.
Grygum: I mean, I'm thinking about.
GM: Alright, alright, I'm… okay, so let me just be clear.
GM: Manshoon cast a spell before you walk down, so you do have a chance to cast a spell, a buff spell, before he walks down.
Daz: Okay.
GM: So I'm just… just to be clear, he's… he… you know, he is evil, after all. So he did walk down, but he cast a spell on himself, as a buff spell.
GM: So he's currently, has mirror images floating around him.
Daz: Is… is he considered a creature?
Daz: For the purposes of the spell.
GM: I now have to look it up.
GM: What are you trying to do? Let me just… let me say what you're trying to do.
Daz: Phantasmal Killer.
GM: Oh, yeah, yeah, that can definitely affect him.
Daz: Okay.
GM: Yeah, sorry, creature… yeah, he's a creature from that perspective.
Daz: I will cast, Phantasmal Killer on him, because I'd like to get him stuck with disadvantage on rolls.
Daz: Whoa.
GM: Alright, what… is that a two-hit.
Daz: We need the Wisdom DC17 save.
Daz: Or he takes 26 points of, psychic damage, and he'll have disadvantage on ability checks and attack rolls for the duration.
Daz: If he's successful, Then he doesn't get the disabilities, and he gets half the damage.
GM: Okay.
Daz: And if he continues to miss the saves, he continues to take the damage again and again and again.
Daz: So it's…
GM: Yeah, I know, I know how that spell works. Alright, so now I'm trying to see what his,
Daz: And I cast it at the fourth level, not at the third.
Daz: Which kind of sucks, because I only got 26. I was hoping more for…
Daz: I rolled a 1, a 9, a 10, and a 6. I guess that's not bad.
GM: Right, so he's already burned.
Daz: Oh wait, that doesn't include the extra.
GM: Yes.
Daz: Oh, above 4.
Daz: Nevermind.
GM: Alright.
Daz: 4 is the minimum.
GM: Correct.
GM: So he's going to first, he's just… he's trying to decide, do I burn my Counterspell here?
GM: He pauses.
GM: He burns the counterspell, he can't cast a spell.
Daz: Sure?
GM: Yeah, no, no, I'm trying to… okay, so he's gonna roll the saving throw.
Daz: Whoa.
GM: That is an 8. Let me just see what his bonuses are.
Daz: That's a… that's a low…
GM: Yeah, I know, but he, but remember, he's the legendary.
Daz: I know, I know, I'm just saying.
GM: But you… He actually makes it, he has a plus 9 on his wisdom.
Daz: So he got… oh, so he got exactly 17?
GM: Yes.
Daz: That sucks. Well, he still… he still took 4… er, 13 points of psychic damage.
GM: Okay, so he takes 13 points of psychic damage. Alright, oop, sorry, that's not… no, he should not have taken…
GM: Right.
GM: Okay. Thorin, Europe. Hold on. He decides…
Grygum: Start at 7.30, what, at…
GM: We can stop here, we can stop here. Okay.
Thorin: We're starting with me. Yes, we're starting. I haven't done anything.
GM: Let me… let me just, put a… let me just put a thing in here.
GM: Boom.
GM: start here.
GM: Just put that label…
Grygum: I think we can use this anti-magic field to our advantage, doing things like, you know, firing at him and then ducking out the door so he can't get back at us as effectively.
GM: Yeah, so Daz, would you want to stay there, sit in the room as his target, or do you want to, like, try to…
Daz: No, no, after I hit him, I want to start heading towards the bridge. I think the more we can, like, hit him a little and then suck him out into the bridge, then we can hit him with crossbows or something.
GM: Alright, so you're going onto the bridge?
Daz: Yeah.
GM: Sounds good.
GM: Okay, so does… that's your position.
GM: Alright.
GM: Alright, we will stop here.
Daz: Thank you all.
GM: Thank you, this is… this is… sorry, this was a little bit overwhelming in terms of keeping all these things in order, but I think we'll… we'll have the big fight with Manshoon next.
Grygum: Oh, it's fine.
GM: Alright, take care, guys.
Thorin: Alright, have a good one.
Daz: Thanks.